<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Diplateevo</title>
        <link>https://www.diplateevo.com</link>
        <description>A blog, by Daniel Kao</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 05:39:18 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>SvelteKit</generator>
        <image>
            <title>Diplateevo</title>
            <url>https://www.diplateevo.com/cover-default.jpg</url>
            <link>https://www.diplateevo.com</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>Copyright 2022, Diplateevo</copyright>
        <atom:link href="https://www.diplateevo.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I'm Reviving this Blog in 2022]]></title>
            <link>https://www.diplateevo.com/looking-to-2022</link>
            <guid>https://www.diplateevo.com/looking-to-2022</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Forget web3, I'm going back to web 1.0.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When I started this blog back in high school, a classmate of mine kindly gave me access to his web host and a WordPress sandbox and let me do whatever I wanted. I started hacking my way around HTML, CSS, PHP, and MySQL, finding a way to break this website almost weekly and trying out as many WordPress plugins and themes as I possibly could. I flouted my parents&#39; computer use curfew by waking up at six in the morning in order to play with my website (or computer games), and the name &quot;diplateevo&quot; came out of an experiment rearranging random letters until I got something unique.</p><p>I started blogging regularly and soon outgrew my borrowed web host. After a few conversations with my father, he agreed to pay for shared hosting on Dreamhost, and I continued developing and vastly overcomplicating my WordPress installation. By the time I graduated college, however, I started working full-time and blog updates became infrequent. I started using Twitter regularly as a way to share my thoughts and connect with people around the world. In fact, part of my decision to ultimately move to Taiwan was spurred by conversations with people I met through Twitter.</p><p>Eventually, I wondered why I was paying nearly $30 a month to host this website that I barely used, and decided to greatly simplify and re-engineer this blog to use a gerry-rigged <a href="https://ghost.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ghost CMS</a> to serve as a static site generator with a frontend written in <a href="https://svelte.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Svelte</a> and <a href="https://sapper.svelte.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sapper</a>, hosted on <a href="https://pages.github.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Github Pages</a>. Hosting costs went to zero, but this blog continued to be dormant.</p><p>My optimism toward social media started going downhill sometime around 2015-2016. It’s hard to pinpoint an exact inflection point, but around that time I started noticing people around me getting information more from internet sources rather than from books, magazines, and newspapers. The explosion of the mobile internet and “the sharing economy” meant that a significant amount of people had their first experience with the web not in the Web 1.0 era, but in the Web 2.0 era on mobile devices.</p><p>Ironically, that was when I first started playing with cryptocurrencies and still optimistic about what changes blockchains might bring to our digital lives. No one knew at the time that Bitcoin was going to reach the valuation it has today, and the mere possibility that it might end up completely worthless is exactly what made it fun, interesting, and worthwhile. The entire experience felt like the alpha release of a cool, low-risk, tech product that I could experiment with. It’s unfortunate that in 2022, it still feels like an alpha product and yet is no longer anywhere near low-risk.</p><h2 id="decentralized-mistrust">Decentralized Mistrust</h2><p>Today, it’s impossible to scroll through my Twitter feed or browse Hacker News without someone arguing about cryptocurrencies, Web3, or the metaverse, espousing ideals about “decentralization” without fully understanding what it means. I want to get away from predatory social media and advertising platforms as much as anyone, but most blockchain applications feel like a frankenstein solution forced onto a problem they were never meant to solve.</p><p>To put it simply, blockchains allow individuals to cooperate with others they don’t trust by placing trust in the network and cryptographic algorithms securing the data. This as an incredible engineering feat and certainly has valuable and appropriate use cases. But just as driving an armored vehicle with a motorcade is overkill and cost / energy inefficient for most transit scenarios, moving all our applications onto blockchain-powered platforms is not going to solve any real problems while only creating more problems. For example, how is a blockchain-powered social media platform going to be any better at solving harassment problems, especially if every single post gets written permanently on-chain? Without any cooperation with legally enforceable regulations, how are so called “smart contracts” going to provide any jurisdiction over the real world?</p><p>Additionally, blockchain protocols are built with mistrust as a default state, which means a lot of redundant energy is spent verifying every single transaction, which is why cryptocurrencies consume exorbitant amounts of energy in return for little actual performance, not to mention the extra amount of engineering required to build, deploy, and support something on the blockchain.</p><h2 id="a-new-old-vision-for-diplateevo">A New (Old) Vision for Diplateevo</h2><p>All that to say, I will not be web3-ifying Diplateevo (whatever that means) anytime soon. As someone who has built a career in frontend engineering, I’ve started to really value simplifying things as much as possible, and creatively thinking about ways to make software more resilient, reliable, and performant. I find that my most productive programming sessions are when I delete more code and write more testing and documentation, because it allows me to rethink and triple check my output.</p><p>I’ve re-engineered this website (yet again) to be even simpler and portable, and have even decided to <a href="https://github.com/dkaoster/www.diplateevo.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">make the whole thing public</a>. It’s still built on <a href="https://svelte.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Svelte</a>, but I’ve migrated to <a href="https://kit.svelte.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SvelteKit</a> and removed Ghost CMS backend in favor of simple <a href="http://archieml.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ArchieML</a> text files to generate a static website. This will allow me the flexibility to do both simple and complex posts, which I plan to do a lot more of in 2022.</p><p>Web 1.0 ftw.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <enclosure url="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2022/01/cover-2022.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Building a Realtime Election Tracker]]></title>
            <link>https://www.diplateevo.com/building-a-realtime-election-tracker-for-taiwans-2020-election</link>
            <guid>https://www.diplateevo.com/building-a-realtime-election-tracker-for-taiwans-2020-election</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[On January 11th, 2020, Taiwan went to the polls to elect their next President and Legislature. For us at the News Lens, we formed a small team of designers, engineers, and editors to build this year’s election tracker.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On January 11th, 2020, Taiwan went to the polls to elect their next President and Legislature. In Taiwan’s short history as a democracy, this election was only the 7th presidential election that Taiwan has held, conducted after months of unrest in Hong Kong and an increasing trend of populism around the world. For us at <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://international.thenewslens.com/">the News Lens</a>, we formed a small team of designers, engineers, and editors to build <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://international.thenewslens.com/interactive/126882">this year’s election tracker</a>.</p><h2 id="product">Product</h2><p>Before we started planning the technical details, we began by thinking about election coverage as a product: What do readers care about? What are their reading habits / usage patterns? Who is our audience?</p><div class="image-wrap full svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="screenshots of different devices" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/Artboard-2.png" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>For starters, we expected that 80% of our readers would be accessing our content from a mobile device, and the large majority would be looking for Chinese content, although we would also make a version for our English readers. We knew that we wanted to display the results as close to realtime as we possible could, and knew that we wanted to cover presidential, district legislators, party legislators, and indigenous legislators. We also knew that we wanted to create an experience that gave readers content for before, during, and after the election, and to make content that could be built upon and referenced in the future.</p><div class="image-wrap  svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="presidential poll tracking" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/Screenshot-2020-01-24-14.34.45.png" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>To begin, we launched our election coverage by doing an aggregation of political polls in Taiwan, giving readers a more holistic view of trends of support for each of the presidential candidates. This not only gave us a way to promote our election coverage, but also gave us a way to test our new, Svelte-based system for building interactive articles and work out some of the kinks before election day. In total, building this tracker took us about two months, with a dedicated engineer and designer working nearly full time on this project.</p><h2 id="maps">Maps</h2><p>Given that the main interaction users make with the election tracker is through the map, the map had to be responsive to user interaction and data updates. To allow users to explore as much of the data as possible, we decided that our map would at have three different layers to interact with.</p><p>The topmost layer is the whole country, including the outer islands that are part of Taiwan’s jurisdiction, followed by 22 counties (縣市). Each of the 22 counties can be further divided into towns (鄉鎮區), and the smallest unit of locality which we did not display is the village (里).</p><p>All of this map data is obtained from <a href="https://data.gov.tw/dataset/7438" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Taiwan’s government website</a> in the form of a 114MB shapefile. Obviously, if we were to directly convert the shapefile to topojson (a format for browsers to draw maps, more on this later), we’d still be looking at a file that is ~90MB in size; far too big to have every user download to their device.</p><p>Moreover, the map needs to be processed for special areas (areas that are part of Taiwan’s jurisdiction but may not be part of an official locality, such as 釣魚台) and relocation of the outer islands so that Kinmen and Lienchiang don’t make the map look too big. At first, I processed a few topojson files using QGIS and the shapefile obtained from the government, but after many failed attempts, (ie incorrect island relocation, missing districts, resulting file too large, too many details removed from the map during compression, etc) I decided to create an API endpoint that would process the map that I want on the fly.</p><div class="image-wrap full svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="dynamic map generating code" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/Artboard-8.png" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>In essence, the API endpoint takes a few parameters:</p><ul><li class="svelte-1e9qspg">Map Version: Due to the fact that these borders will change based on redistricting or otherwise, I wanted to future-proof this API by allowing future maps to be easily versioned by year.</li><li class="svelte-1e9qspg">Locality Depth: Do we want the borders of the county, town, village, or district?</li><li class="svelte-1e9qspg">Specific Locality: Do we want the borders of a specific county, town, village, or district?</li><li class="svelte-1e9qspg">Simplification Level: How simplified do we want the resulting JSON file to be? More simplification and quantization means smaller file sizes but also a loss of detail.</li><li class="svelte-1e9qspg">Condensation of Outer Islands: Do we want a map where Kinmen and Lienchiang are where they are geographically or do we want to see them closer to mainland Taiwan?</li></ul><p>However, because legislative districts are not exactly correlated to any one of the existing locales, we had to separately process all of the locales of each of the legislative districts. Because a whole day of searching could not turn up a shapefile for Taiwan’s legislative districts, we decided to create the map ourselves based on which counties, towns, or villages, belonged to which district.</p><div class="image-wrap full svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="custom map making" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/Artboard-3.png" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><h3 id="svg-vs-canvas">SVG vs Canvas</h3><p>After constructing a reliable way to generate our topojson, the next question was figuring out how to display it in our browser. The naive approach is to <a href="https://medium.com/@mbostock/command-line-cartography-part-1-897aa8f8ca2c" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">simply render the topojson to a SVG</a>. However, the problem with this is that SVGs use the DOM, which means that changes or user interactions with a complex SVG is slow and resource intensive. Add locale labels and mouse interactions and suddenly your SVG implementation slows to a crawl.</p><p>The alternative is to use a canvas for display and an invisible SVG for interaction. This allows us to avoid expensive DOM operations of maintaining and manipulating the color of each locale on the map and instead use the canvas API to paint our map, while maintaining a SVG just to keep track of when users interact. In my very unscientific benchmarking on my own machine, I found that SVGs needed to be about twice a simplified compared to canvas in order to achieve similar performance. More about <a href="https://observablehq.com/@rdmurphy/combining-html-canvas-svg-flatbush-for-super-efficient-hov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this method here</a>.</p><p>The optimizations that I could have done on the map are endless. If we were to further optimize the map, I would recommend using some kind of WebGL implementation, potentially <a href="https://docs.mapbox.com/mapbox-gl-js/api/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MapboxGL</a> to make map rendering performance even better, but a canvas approach was good enough for this use case.</p><h2 id="data-pipeline">Data Pipeline</h2><p>The data for our election tracker was obtained from the Central Election Committee, which gives us a 3MB JSON file of all the data anytime it is updated. Because this JSON file is so large and can take up to 5 seconds to download from the Central Election Committee, we decided to only fetch it at a regular cadence and process / store it into a database we can control and scale.</p><div class="image-wrap full svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="data pipeline screenshot" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/Artboard-9.png" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>To do this, we used a cron job that would fetch the latest data from the Central Election Committee every minute, and separate out presidential and legislative results before storing it into Google Datastore.</p><p>Then, in order to indicate when a candidate has won, we connected a Google Spreadsheet that allowed our editors to manually mark when a race had been won. The system would then use that data to display the winner on the frontend. As it turns out, this became a problem on the night of the election, which I expand more on in the “lessons learned” section.</p><h2 id="election-rules-edge-cases">Election Rules Edge Cases</h2><p>In terms of electoral rules, Taiwan follows a simple majority-wins policy for electing it’s president, which is easy to display on a map. However, legislative races follow a fairly complex system:</p><ul><li class="svelte-1e9qspg">Taiwan’s legislature has a total of 113 seats.</li><li class="svelte-1e9qspg">73 district legislators are elected through a majority-wins policy for each of the 73 designated districts of Taiwan.</li><li class="svelte-1e9qspg">34 party legislators are elected through a party-vote system, in which voters vote on a party, and all parties that obtain over 5% of the overall vote get to assign legislators based on the proportion of votes they receive. The legislators of a party elected through this system must be &gt;50% female, according to the order they are ranked in their party list.</li><li class="svelte-1e9qspg">6 indigenous legislators are elected by two three-member constituencies, picking the top three legislators for each plains and highlands indigenous constituencies.</li></ul><div class="image-wrap  svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="towns vs legislative districts" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/Artboard-6.png" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>This logic poses a few challenges. First of all, the topmost level we can display for district legislators is the district itself, because we can’t calculate the color for a county that has multiple districts with different races.</p><div class="image-wrap  svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="legislative district colors" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/Artboard-5.png" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>Second, because indigenous legislature races elect the top three candidates for each plains and highlands indigenous groups, simply coloring a district with the party of the first-place candidate does not reflect the true breakdown of the vote. Thus, we decided to take the top three candidates and add up the votes based on their political parties, then take the color of the party with the most votes.</p><div class="image-wrap  svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="party vote order" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/Artboard-4.png" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>Third, because of the gender rule for party votes, legislators of a party that get elected through this method do not necessarily correspond with the order that they are placed in the party list. As a result, we have to build an algorithm to determine skip over the next male legislator in the list if there are already too many men.</p><h2 id="post-election-graphics">Post-Election Graphics</h2><p>Another large element of our election coverage was the graphics that we post to social media such as Facebook and Instagram. Because we wanted to be able to generate social media optimized graphics as fast as possible, we needed a method faster than designers plugging in election results into graphic. To achieve this, we built an internal website that would dynamically generate SVGs with the latest data from the Central Election Committee.</p><div class="image-wrap full svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="Dynamic Graphic Generation" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/Artboard-7.png" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>To achieve this, designers would first come up with the design of the graphics in the form of an adobe illustrator document. Then we took those graphics and exported each one into a separate SVG. Because SVG files are a XML-based specification, we can port these into our web application in order to make content within the SVG dynamic.</p><p>The great thing about using SVGs in this way is that it is language and tool agnostic, which means you can use whatever existing templating language / framework you use to generate these graphics. In our case, we fitted it into an internal website that the social media team can directly access to download the generated SVG or a PNG format to be posted on social media platforms like Facebook and Instagram.</p><h2 id="monitoring">Monitoring</h2><p>Another critical piece of election-preparedness was making sure that we knew everything that was happening with our web application at all times. To monitor the health of the application and make sure that everything scaled properly, we set up a grafana dashboard that kept track of server errors, response latency, upstream API connections, cache hit ratios, as well as the standard CPU, memory, and database metrics.</p><div class="image-wrap full svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="Grafana Monitoring" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/DSC04709.jpg" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>By having the web application directly report metrics to prometheus, it was much easier to get the fine grained metrics specific to elections that we cared about. Because we had taken the time to integrate key metrics into prometheus, when errors began to show up during the election, we were able to immediately know what was causing the error.</p><h2 id="svelte">Svelte</h2><p>Although React has been possibly the most popular front-end framework to use these days, one of the questions I find interesting to ask during interviews is “Under what circumstances is React not a good framework to use? When would you recommend not using React?” This is a question that stumps many less-experienced engineers and people without a good grasp of what React really does in the browser under the hood. In fact, I believe that there are many situations under which React is not a good choice, and building interactives in a news environment is one of them.</p><div class="image-wrap  svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="svelte logo" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/svelte.png" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>News organizations have a very different development and deployment cycle than tech companies do, requiring tighter deadlines, faster feedback loops, and more bespoke flexibility. Thus, I decided to use <a href="https://svelte.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Svelte</a>, giving us the following main advantages among many:</p><ul><li class="svelte-1e9qspg">Development speed: Given the amount of work to be done within a short amount of time, I decided that Svelte would be much faster to write than React, giving faster development and feedback times. Using Sapper with Svelte would also allow me to write the server-side data APIs quickly and easily.</li><li class="svelte-1e9qspg">Bundled JS Size: Because Svelte runs as a compiler, it’s able to build and include only the code that your applications needs, making the compiled bundle much smaller than a React application.</li></ul><p>If you’re interested in learning more about Svelte, there are many <a href="https://svelte.dev/tutorial/basics" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">tutorials to help you get started</a>.</p><h2 id="lessons-learned">Lessons Learned</h2><h3 id="load-test">Load Test</h3><p>The biggest problem we saw on election night was that the site was down for ~1 hour due to high traffic. Specifically, it wasn’t the servers on our end that could not take the traffic, it was our usage of Google Sheets that caused Google to lock our google spreadsheet when the flow of traffic became too large. After Google locked out requests to the spreadsheet, our system started responding to downstream users with 500 errors, causing the entire site to be inoperable.</p><p>The solution was to first disconnect the spreadsheet from our services, which brought both our service and the google spreadsheet back online. Then, we implemented a quick function that would prevent the service from requesting data from the google spreadsheet so often. This brought everything back online.</p><p>The lesson here is that, unless you fully load test your entire system before the election, you never know what problems will be caused when traffic increases by a few orders of magnitude. Often, third-party services such as Google Docs will have their own unwritten throughput and bandwidth limits.</p><h3 id="have-a-clear-incident-response-plan">Have a Clear Incident Response Plan</h3><p>No matter how much planning you do in preparation of the big day, incidents are always likely to happen and things will never go exactly according to plan. That said, after you’ve made all the preparation you can possibly make, the next important thing to plan for is how to respond when things do not go as plan. In our case, by dividing up responsibilities we had a basic level of responsibilities when things went awry, but it would have been more advantageous to rehearse a few scenarios.</p><p>Namely, when the site goes down, it is important to define who will fix the problem and who will report the status to the rest of the team. It is hard for one person to do both, lest the person trying to fix the problem becomes bombarded with too many inquiries about the current status and is unable to concentrate on fixing the problem.</p><h2 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping Up</h2><p>In conclusion, I hope the process we used and the lessons we learned can be built upon by the community, allowing future elections and similar events to be faster, more efficient, and better experiences for our readers and our organizations. I’m sure that our processes will continue to evolve, and I hope we can continue to learn better workflows and collaboration processes.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <enclosure url="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/Artboard-1.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Memories of New York]]></title>
            <link>https://www.diplateevo.com/memories-of-new-york</link>
            <guid>https://www.diplateevo.com/memories-of-new-york</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Next to a stand of dragonfruit, durian, guavas, lychee, and mangosteen on the corner of Main Street and 41st Rd, a nondescript door presents itself in a drab, frosted white.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Next to a stand of dragonfruit, durian, guavas, lychee, and mangosteen on the corner of Main Street and 41st Rd, a nondescript door presents itself in a drab, frosted white. Above the door the words “Golden Shopping Mall” appear in a golden sans-serif font, which are the only clues that through the door and down the stairs lie culinary gems of New York City.</p><p>Downstairs, you’ll find Tianjin Dumpling House, Lan Zhou Noodles, and the original Xian’s Famous Foods, all cramped into a tiny, poorly ventilated space. We all have our vices – mine include the lamb dumplings from Tianjin Dumpling House, which I’ve always kept a bag of sitting in my freezer. They’re plump, juicy, thicc, and life-changing.</p><p>New York City. A city that has attracted immigrants from around the world for a million different reasons, where a cacophony of languages, cultures, and experiences harmonize. Flushing represents an experience of Asian-America that shares cultural roots yet is different in every other way from my hometown of Cupertino. As I’ve gotten to know Asian-Americans who grew up in Queens, our conversations have uncovered stories of children who had to translate for their parents at a young age or hide in work closets because there wasn’t enough money for childcare.</p><p>My grandparents came to the United States with roughly enough money to buy a dining table and a TV, stopping in Flushing for less than a year before moving to Houston where they live today. In a recent conversation with my grandma, she told me about the restaurant on Main Street where she would buy roast duck during the first six months they spent in the States as they learned English. Today, scenes of the immigrant work ethic are still visible in Flushing, where new immigrants continue to live the life that my grandparents experienced thirty years ago.</p><div class="image-wrap full svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="Shanghainese Food" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/IMG_20180210_171604.jpg" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>Down the little alley known as 40th Road is Shanghai You Garden, where they make soup dumplings by hand in the front of the restaurant for all to see, reminding me of Taiwan’s legendary Din Tai Fung. Walk a few doors down and you’ll find Yifang Taiwan Fruit Tea, a gem of Taiwan’s most notorious culinary export: boba.</p><p>There’s no contest when it comes to two types of foods that I will never tire of: noodles and tacos. Despite what the average New Yorker may believe, New York City is a medieval backwater when it comes to tacos – sure you have Los Tacos #1, but anyone who’s had any random taco truck in Los Angeles can tell you that Los Tacos is merely passable in comparison. When it comes to noodles, however, New York’s got an endless variety: Singapore Laksa, Khao Soy, Beef Noodle Soup, Bun Bo Hue, Biang Biang Noodles from places like Tasty Hand Pulled Noodles, Taste Good Malaysian Cuisine, Dun Huang Beef Noodle, and so on.</p><div class="image-wrap full svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="Filipino Food" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/IMG_20180624_145920.jpg" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>It’s been almost three months since I’ve left New York City, but I still get flashbacks of the anticipation on 7 train between Mets-Willets Point and Flushing Main St. Or the time that, upon finishing an episode of Parts Unknown at 11pm, my friend and I ventured into the cold for the same living octopus that we just watched Bourdain eat on TV. I’ve tried so many new cuisines in New York City – Sichuan, Colombian, Greek, Uyghur, Tibetan, Brazilian, Malaysian, all without venturing more than a few subway stops from my apartment in Queens.</p><p>I’d love to say that every place I’ve tried in New York has been nothing short of stellar, but the reality is quite the opposite: for every place that has left me with a new appreciation for a certain type of noodle, meat, or vegetable, many others have left me disappointed or unsatisfied. I’ll never understand why New York City has a disproportionately high number of mediocre and expensive ramen restaurants, or the poke shops that are more pleasing to the instagram than the taste buds.</p><p>I think back on it now with a kind of nostalgic Stockholm Syndrome. Faded are the irritations of getting to see sunlight for mere minutes everyday, fighting for personal space on a subway train with a broken AC, and the city noises that never shut up. These days, I’m soaking up all California has to offer by wandering through the desert, the forest, the mountains, or the beaches, wondering how I ever was able to function in such an excessive concrete jungle. The food certainly made it more stomachable.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <enclosure url="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/DSC00224.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How the Internet is Redefining Media and Politics Around the World]]></title>
            <link>https://www.diplateevo.com/digital-disobedience-internet-redefining-media-politics-around-world</link>
            <guid>https://www.diplateevo.com/digital-disobedience-internet-redefining-media-politics-around-world</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Drastic changes in technology and media are heavily influencing the pace and nature of change in our modern political establishment, increasing global uncertainty as more citizens are empowered to take action through digital tools and the internet.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve always interpreted the Second Amendment very literally: a provision that allows citizens of the United States the right to own firearms. But in a recent conversation with a startup founder, he suggested that it could also be interpreted to include digital encryption as a kind of modern weapon for self defense.</p><p>I’m no lawyer or constitutional historian, but even if that snippet of legalese cannot be stretched to protect privacy via methods of digital encryption, the thought illustrates how far we’ve come from the world that the framers of the constitution imagined while writing the initial governance for our country. The regulatory debates of our current social-political landscapes would fly over the heads of even the most forward-thinking founding fathers.</p><p>The freedom of assembly, listed right next to freedom of speech and freedom of the press in the First Amendment, is a provision guaranteed by our nation that protects the right of individuals to peacefully assemble for any reason or circumstance. Throughout America’s history, grassroots assembly has empowered individuals to organize and protest, enabling much of the change that has happened in American history.</p><p>Today, digital communications has become the medium for much of the organizing that formerly took place by physical assembly, stretching the concept of assembly beyond merely physical convenings. In this world, encryption becomes a vital part of giving people the ability to speak freely. In that sense, I’d argue that encryption has more to do with the First Amendment than the second, despite encryption not being mentioned anywhere in the original constitution.</p><p>It is this type of modern refactoring that lends itself to a constant need to rethink and refine our systems of government, technology, and social relations. But while every era presents a different set of complex challenges, it would be naive to assert that this notion of political change is new or uniquely of our time. From the renaissance to global colonization to world wars to the internet and every little thing in between, people have debated the very nature of how political and regulatory systems have functioned in a way that I will call “technocratic political innovation”.</p><p>By “technocratic”, I don’t mean someone who is leading with the intent of increasing the implementation of digital devices and systems, I mean someone with a scientific, quantitative, and research driven approach to improve outcomes in a political system. In this sense, thinkers like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexis_de_Tocqueville" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">de Tocqueville</a> could potentially be considered technocratic, even if they would call a modern smartphone some kind of witchcraft.</p><div class="image-wrap full svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="Photo of the Arab Spring" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/1318034247206.jpg" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>There’s no doubt that technology is a powerful tool for organizing and taking action. We’ve seen how things like social media and digital communications have been critical infrastructure in instances such as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab_Spring" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">widely hailed Arab Spring</a>. If we’re not careful, however, it’s easy to give too much credit to social media for the success of political movements that resulted from hundreds of thousands of people organizing and establishing their movement. And as much as social media has the power to unite, it has in certain cases also isolated us from the very movements we seek to partake in. Social media accelerates globalization in a way that connects me to similar people around the world while distancing me from the waiter at the restaurant I had lunch at.</p><p>Faulting social media platforms for ignorant bubbles isn’t entirely fair. People lived in filter bubbles long before the internet ever existed. However, social media is causing an upheaval in the way our filter bubbles operate without explicitly intending to.</p><blockquote><p>If social media unintentionally reconfigured our filter bubbles to break down physical distance at the expense of increasing digital distance, civic media is an intentional effort to counteract the growing distance between people.</p></blockquote><p>All over the world, pockets of people are prototyping new ways of digital civic participation in hopes to be successful enough to scale across an entire party, city, or a nation. The term hacktivism has been recently popularized to describe this sort of activism, across a spectrum from anonymous digital vigilantes to publicly-funded digital governance efforts. While hacktivists around the world may not be of the same political leanings, languages, or belief systems, hacktivism is a force that is only increasing in use internationally, and choosing to ignore these movements is choosing to ignore an increasingly potent force in global politics.</p><p>The drastic changes in technology and media are only going to amplify and accelerate the pace of change in our modern political establishment, propelling us into more global uncertainty. With the election of Donald Trump and populists around the world, not only are traditional politicians likely an endangered class of individuals, an even stronger wave of Millennials and Gen-Zers are waiting to one day inherit the power from today’s leaders.</p><p>It is a very crucial time in world history, and the stories of decisions made by tomorrow’s leaders today are going to have a greater impact than the decisions of today’s leaders today. <a href="http://www.ianbremmer.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ian Bremmer</a> talks about 2016 being a transition between a world led by the United States known as <a href="https://www.eurasiagroup.net/live-post/it-really-is-the-end-of-the-world-as-we-know-it" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">“Pax Americana” to being a world without a clear leader known as “G-Zero”</a>.</p><p>In a G-Zero world, no country or group of countries has the leverage to unilaterally champion a single worldview. In fact, a G-Zero world means that no two countries are on the same page in terms of economic, domestic, or foreign policy, leaving the world without a country that is able to advance a specific international agenda. And as the result of globalization, corporations are sitting on greater vaults of wealth, routing assets and finances through many countries with conflicting interests, causing certain countries that would otherwise be in stark conflicts to have a somewhat stable relationship.</p><p>One argument to explain why the European Union has been relatively free of conflict in the past few decades can be attributed to the EU, specifically the way that the euro has bound the european countries together economically. A similar argument could be made about the US and China: that the two countries are so interdependent that neither side is willing to risk a conflict for fear of repercussions in their own country.</p><p>However, the economics are not enough to prevent tensions between countries. As tensions continue to escalate both between and within countries, causing democratic upheavals such as the massive protests that are taking place in response to Trump’s election in the US, Park’s impeachment in South Korea, Erdogan’s eroding of democratic systems, history tells us that we have the conditions for significant changes likely started from single individuals or group of individuals.</p><p>But despite the fact that we’re currently witnessing an alarming number of nationalistic world leaders rise to power, people today are better prepared to face these leaders than we have ever been.</p><h2 id="the-historical-rise-of-non-state-actors">The Historical Rise of Non-State Actors</h2><p>The role of everyday individuals shaping the political direction runs in parallel with the technologies that everyday people have access to. Technology enables or inhibits the way that ideas are shared and movements are organized. Thus, to think that media and technology are separate is misguided; technology has always been about media, whether that be distributing an idea to as many people as possible or intentionally anonymizing and limiting who knows about something.</p><p>In 1969, an employee of RAND corporation named <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Ellsberg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Daniel Ellsberg</a> began making covert photocopies of classified documents about the Vietnam war. Being in an era before files were edited digitally, it took over the span of a year for Ellsberg to manually make copies of the documents in his off-work hours. As the news broke on June 13th, 1971, the story confirmed the suspicions people had that the government was more involved in Vietnam than they were publicly admitting.</p><p>Fast forward 40 years later, an intelligence analyst named <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chelsea_Manning" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Bradley Manning</a> was faced with a similar choice that Ellsberg faced: whether to leak documents that detailed US involvement abroad. However, the stark difference between Ellsberg and Manning was that it took Manning less than a day to copy out an archive of data hundreds of times larger than the Pentagon Papers, a cache that would have taken Ellsberg roughly 18 years to copy the way he copied the Pentagon Papers.</p><blockquote><p>Publishing, leaking, and whistleblowing have all become much more accessible from the time of the printing press to the internet, enabling anyone today to use cryptography and internet anonymity tools to avoid surveillance and sound the alarms on governments. Individuals such as Julian Assange can single-handedly create political nightmares for governments, forcing them to be accountable in public to the things they said privately.</p></blockquote><p>And Internet whistleblowing is just one example of how a small group of people are changing the way that governments and politicians operate. Just as the rise of internet media has caused print newspapers and journalists to completely change the way that they operate, it is also forcing groups to change of how they establish influence and power.</p><p>One of the most widely cited examples of the Internet’s role in political organizing has been the Arab Spring; where protests organized largely through digital tools radically impacted the relationship governments had with their citizens, including overthrowing leaders and other incumbent regimes. But around the world, the Arab Spring is only one example of how technology is being used by individuals to circulate ideas and incite political action.</p><h2 id="partido-de-la-red-democracyos-and-argentina">Partido de la Red, DemocracyOS, and Argentina</h2><p>The Outerlands was just the kind of restaurant you’d expect to find in San Francisco. The decor consists of reclaimed wood and bare lightbulbs hanging in a way that is most-definitely more expensive than appears. Here, founders from all over the world are attracted to the prospect of starting their own technology company and achieve the now-cliche belief that they are “changing the world”.</p><p>Wearing a hoodie that is typical for Silicon Valley technology types, Santiago walked in after a morning of wrangling code for his new internet-democracy platform. Most stories of startup founders moving to Silicon Valley are similarly unique: as an outsider in their native environment, they made some sort of application or technology, got accepted to an accelerator in Silicon Valley such as YCombinator, and moved out to San Francisco.</p><p>Santiago fits right in in San Francisco: passionate about the potential for technology to impact incumbent processes, Santiago called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satoshi_Nakamoto" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Satoshi Nakamoto’s blockchain</a> the next great invention behind Gutenberg’s printing press and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_Berners-Lee" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tim Berners-Lee’s world wide web</a>. In fact, Santiago shared that he documented the birth of his daughter on a blockchain as a publicly permanent declaration of her birth.</p><p>But where Santiago stands out is in his history with political activism starting in his hometown of Buenos Aires. In 2012, Santiago started <a href="http://partidodelared.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Partido de la Red</a>, a political party in Buenos Aires that was inspired by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delegative_democracy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">liquid democracy</a>.</p><blockquote><p>To someone used to following American politics, starting a political party seems more difficult than landing a human on the moon.</p></blockquote><p>Traditionally dominated by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peronism" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Peronism</a>, opposing political parties in Argentina have had a long history playing second fiddle to the long-incumbent Peronist ideal that has won three-quarters of the presidential elections since it started in 1946. The Peronist ideal, rejecting both capitalism and communism, is not a political ideal easily captured by traditional western politics.</p><p>Since the ideals for Peronism were laid down in the 1940s, it’s flexibility in political views has allowed it to maintain dominance through a series of coups, martial law, corruption, political violence, and all the other things Argentina has gone through, much of which is still felt today. Walking through Plaza de Mayo, for instance, it’s hard to miss the white scarves painted on the ground as a symbol of the Mothers that would gather to protest state terrorism that kidnapped children without explanation.</p><div class="image-wrap full svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="Plaza de Mayo" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/IMG_20160925_154023.jpg" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>Nevertheless, in an attempt to address corruption in the political system, the Net Party was founded by Santiago as a grassroots attempt to build a political system around the voice of the people, implementing a voting platform to allow citizens to essentially act as a digital parliament. By implementing <a href="http://democracyos.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DemocracyOS</a>, an internet platform for collecting votes from citizens, representatives from the Net Party are better able to legislate in accordance to their constituents.</p><p>Liquid democracy, also known as delegative democracy, is an idea that builds on the concept of every citizen being able to elect their representative. Through liquid democracy, citizens are able to vote by vesting power in delegates rather than representatives.</p><blockquote><p>The difference between a delegate and a representative is that the barrier to entry of becoming a delegate is much lower than that of becoming a representative, and that citizens can shift power between delegates much more easily than they can representatives. Such a system aims to give more flexibility to each citizen, allowing individuals to become more or less involved at their choosing, and being better able to keep delegates accountable.</p></blockquote><p>I visited the DemocracyOS office in Buenos Aires to learn more about the open source project. The office is about the size of a large living room, complete with a loft that adds a few more desks for people to work. Since it’s inception, DemocracyOS has been implemented by governments in Argentina, Brazil, Spain, France, Finland, Hungary, and Colombia.</p><p>During my visit to the DemocracyOS office, the CTO of DemocracyOS Guido Vilariño, walked me through the code powering DemocracyOS, as I made my first pull request into the Node.js powered application. The ease at which I am able to personally contribute to this project and so many around the world speaks to the interconnectedness of global communities, allowing projects such as DemocracyOS to draw from a global group of volunteers and developers.</p><p>To Guido, DemocracyOS describes a future he is working to see to fruition. In our wide ranging conversation, Guido spoke with a guided sense of pragmatism recognizing that progress toward change requires intentional compromises, even if that means DemocracyOS is not quite implemented according to his ideals. Everyone who is a part of the efforts for Partido de La Red and DemocracyOS share a belief that the internet is having and will have irreversible effects on politics, starting with their efforts in Buenos Aires.</p><p>It’s hard to imagine a system like DemocracyOS existing prior to the internet, as the logistical challenge of maintaining a liquid democracy system would be impossible without the aid of computers to keep track of the decisions made by each person. It’s still far too early to call DemocracyOS’s implementation of liquid democracy a success, but it’s not a stretch to say that DemocracyOS has impacted Buenos Aires in a tangible way, despite all the setbacks it has experienced.</p><p>The vision for DemocracyOS isn’t a partisan appeal, but one they hope to implement at a systemic level. However, because the Net Party is a political party, it is vulnerable to the same political partisanship that any party is subject to. It didn’t take long for Santiago to discover two problems. First, that forcing transparency into a system through political means is going to face pushback from the people benefitting from incumbent systems. And second, that people may use these tools of transparency as a political play to appear more transparent without actually becoming more transparent.</p><p>Today, Santiago no longer works on DemocracyOS. Emboldened instead by a mission that is broader and more ambitious in scope, Santiago tells me about the potential for the blockchain to give power back to the people. Calling his new project <a href="http://democracy.earth/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Democracy Earth</a>, Santiago hopes providing smart contracts via a blockchain for transparent decision making can bring back power to individuals.</p><p>The idea of a post-nation state world, as Democracy Earth is preparing for, is hard to picture given the state of international affairs today. And even if such a world will eventually come to pass, it’s hard to predict how we get to that day.</p><h2 id="vtaiwan-and-the-sunflower-movement">vTaiwan and the Sunflower Movement</h2><p>Beyond being known for it’s culture of endless street food, Taiwan is arguably the most progressive country in Asia. With a population of 23 million people, Taiwan is comparable in population to Australia. But because of historic geopolitical tensions with China, Taiwan’s relationship with the world is contentious and complicated. Outside of Taiwan, little has been understood about the dramatic political changes starting from Japanese rule in 1895 to the ending of martial law in 1987 to the first free election in 1996 to the vibrant democracy it is today.</p><p>Despite being a young, progressive democracy, Taiwan’s internal politics have been rooted in deep controversy. Still formally known as the Republic of China after the nationalists fled mainland China to Taiwan in 1949, the tensions between the Republic of China and the People’s Republic of China have never been resolved. Today, only 2.4% of people between the ages of 20-29 in Taiwan identify themselves as Chinese.</p><p>The last time I was in Taiwan was 2005, when my travel experiences were still very much filtered through the itinerary set up by my parents, including visits to the zoo and other family excursions. But as I landed in Taiwan this past December, this time I was on my own: determined to ask hard questions about the sweeping, undeniable changes happening in Asia and around the world.</p><p>As a descendant of Taiwanese ancestry myself, uncovering the historical events along my lineage often left me perplexed, shocked, and in disbelief as I walked through the streets that raised my parents and grandparents. My grandparents have seen multiple cycles of politics in Taiwan, from growing up under Japanese colonialism and learning Japanese as a part of primary education to the Taiwan it is today.</p><p>In 2016, Taiwan elected its first female president <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsai_Ing-wen" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tsai Ing Wen</a>, the former chairwoman of the Democratic People’s Party. Taiwan’s DPP, although with it’s own set of shortcomings, has positioned itself in modern years as being the progressive party advocating for LGBT rights, workers, and other typically liberal political ideologies. The DPP has significant anti-China sentiments, leaning on the side of independence from China.</p><p>As the public perception in Taiwan drifts further away from a historic Chinese identity, the Taiwanese identity becomes increasingly distinct from that of the Chinese. It is under these conditions that younger generations are forming their own national identities, growing up only knowing their country as a nation independent from China. I couldn’t help but ponder how easily I could have been Taiwan-raised, but for better or worse life dealt me a US passport instead of a Taiwanese one.</p><p>Economically, Taiwan was once the world’s factory. Everything used to come with “Made in Taiwan” tags and stickers. Known as one of the four tigers of Asia (the other three being Hong Kong, Singapore, and South Korea), Taiwan’s GDP grew at exceptionally high rates between the 1960s and the 1990s.</p><blockquote><p>But today, China is developing economically at rates unlike anything the world has ever seen before, causing Taiwan and other neighbors in the Asia-Pacific to cede markets to China because they can no longer compete.</p></blockquote><p>In a post pax-americana world, China stands to surpass the United States in global leadership, although it’s unlikely to happen in the near future. It is this rapid consolidation of economic and geopolitical power that is worrying the Taiwanese; a political stalemate causing Taiwan to pay extremely close attention to how China treats Hong Kong as a premonition of what Taiwan itself is likely to face.</p><div class="image-wrap full svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="Freedom Plaza" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/IMG_20161231_113624.jpg" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>It is these circumstances in Taiwan that provides fertile ground for new political experiments. One effort to digitize civic participation in Taiwan is led by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Audrey_Tang" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Audrey Tang</a>, the youngest and first transgender official in Taiwan’s executive government. Audrey represents a new generation of political leaders, one that grew up with the internet, recognizes globalization, and is tasked with bringing a technology mindset into old, bureaucratic processes.</p><p>Audrey spends much of her time working on <a href="https://www.vtaiwan.org.tw/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">vTaiwan</a>. vTaiwan is a liquid democracy platform that resembles DemocracyOS. Like DemocracyOS, vTaiwan gives everyday citizens the ability to weigh in on many issues that are important to them, allowing them to be more directly involved in their country’s politics. Through vTaiwan, citizens have participated in more transparent government conversations.</p><p>Audrey calls vTaiwan “a working implementation of multi-stakeholder consultation and crowd-sourced agenda setting”. From the outset, the challenge facing such a platform is making it a place for everyone, and avoiding it from skewing out in favor of one demographic or another.</p><p>This type of deliberative democracy was born out of the Sunflower Student Movement of 2014. As a prime example of the kind of organization that young people are willing and active in, demonstrators occupied the legislature for weeks in 2014 as a backlash to a proposed trade deal between Taiwan and China. The scale of such demonstrations was unprecedented, as the legislature has never been occupied by citizens in the history of Taiwan.</p><div class="image-wrap  svelte-1swarl"><img loading="lazy" alt="Sunflower Movement" src="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/sunflower-movement.jpg" width="100%" class="svelte-1swarl">  </div><p>In the resolution of the Sunflower Movement, the students declared that one of their goals was to bring deliberation of policies into the community, bringing an even more open democracy to citizens.</p><p>As I learned about Taiwan’s history with little prerequisite knowledge, the biases from the different accounts and takes on historical events are obvious in a way that my own biases are not. The media landscape in Taiwan, although existing in a country that promotes free press, struggles with many of the same issues we see around the world. The drop in advertising and print revenue is placing a larger financial burden on publications in the US and around the world. But an additional problem facing Taiwan can be traced to cross-strait relations, creating an environment where pro-China publications are likely to receive funding from China, leaving other publications in Taiwan less staffed and resourced.</p><p><a href="http://thediplomat.com/authors/j-michael-cole/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">J Michael Cole</a> moved to Taiwan as a journalist nearly a decade ago, and after reporting for organizations such as the <a href="http://www.taipeitimes.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Taipei Times</a>, he has recently started a new Taiwan-focused media organization called Taiwan Sentinel founded with the goal of providing in-depth reporting on Taiwan to an international audience.</p><p>In a brief conversation at the launch of Taiwan Sentinel, J Michael spoke about how even the top news organizations in the world have a hard time covering Taiwan. Austin Ramzy, a foreign correspondent for the New York Times, was forced out of China in 2014 and decided to relocate to Taipei to become the first Times journalist to be based out of Taiwan. Upon arriving, Austin met with J Michael only to realize how starkly different Taiwan is from mainland China.</p><p>The number of western journalists covering Taiwan is still next to none, but without a proper array of journalists, it’s hard for Americans and others to recognize the gravity of events happening in Taiwan.</p><p>After Tsai and Trump spoke over the phone following Trump’s election, a media firestorm erupted in response to Trump being the first head of state to speak with a Taiwanese head of state since diplomatic relations were cut off under Nixon. This media firestorm was highly critical in western outlets, but highly optimistic to the Taiwanese. Many Taiwanese saw it as a reconciliation of diplomatic relations between the two countries, but unfortunately, relations between Taiwan and the US are unlikely to improve under Trump.</p><p>These are the kinds of events that, when reported well, have the ability to shape popular opinion with a broader understanding of geopolitical relationships, prompting people to organize in ways such as the Sunflower movement.</p><h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2><p>One way to measure the health of a democratic nation is how it protects a citizen’s human rights via rule of law, including protections of speech, assembly, press, voting, etc. However, another way to assess the health of a democracy is to look at how civically engaged it’s citizens are.</p><p>The measure of what is protected by law in a country is often an imperfect picture of whether a country’s people are benefactors and users of a democratic (or not so democratic) system. In fact, it’s possible to argue that the democratic health of a nation has more to do with how active citizens are civically than the agendas and laws written by the leaders: it’s the difference between what the system allows and how people are actually using the system.</p><p>The 2016 US presidential election saw less than 55% of voters turning out to vote, putting voter turnout in the model democracy lower than the majority of other countries. The decay of American democracy wasn’t in the fact that an inexperienced outsider won the electoral college, but that millions of Americans decided that they couldn’t be bothered to vote. Thus, despite the fact that laws in the US protect citizens’ rights to vote (voter ID laws and suppression aside), America’s democracy is threatened by a constant political apathy.</p><p>Whether or not you blame this outcome on a biased media and fake news on social media, news media often serves as the catalyst for political organization and action, manifesting itself as engagements with online platforms, physical protests, lawsuits, or anything else.</p><p>By the standards of participation, the measure of success for platforms like vTaiwan and DemocracyOS may not be so much the legislation or opportunities for civic engagement that they bring, but how it enables citizens to become more politically active. Being digital in nature, internet platforms such as the ones we’ve explored tend to skew toward younger, tech-savvy, educated citizens. The benefits of asynchronous, location-agnostic organizing also struggle to making sure a diverse set of voices are present in the constructive conversations and deliberations.</p><p>However, despite these challenges, digital platforms for civic engagement will continue to evolve, even as nations continue to wrestle with how to best regulate an internet that is not bounded by borders, easily manipulable, and constantly evolving to give their citizens new ways to engage, while also properly curbing cyberattacks.</p><p>Whether it be the blockchain, even more ubiquitous mobile devices, or smarter internet regulations, it’s inevitable that the final frontier for the internet revolution is going to be civic engagement, and it’s going to take far more than a president who uses Twitter to get us there.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <enclosure url="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2020/08/IMG_20161231_113624.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Technology Builds Humans – Notes and Review of “What Technology Wants”]]></title>
            <link>https://www.diplateevo.com/technology-builds-humans-notes-and-review-of-what-technology-wants</link>
            <guid>https://www.diplateevo.com/technology-builds-humans-notes-and-review-of-what-technology-wants</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Despite the fact that humans have been developing technology since the dawn of time, technology is still completely misunderstood.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Despite the fact that humans have been developing technology since the dawn of time, technology is still completely misunderstood.</p><p>When we hear the word technology, our first inclination is to think of our iPhones or computers interacting with the internet. If you’re a little more technically inclined, you may think about writing code or working with certain tools. And maybe if you’re a little bit more cognizant of your lives and culture (or are a parent), you may think about the effects of technology as it applies to areas of child development, social interactions, or otherwise.</p><p>But when viewed from an even larger perspective, we find that technology is so much more than all of that. Kevin Kelly does a phenomenal job at exploring technology and what he coins as the “technium” in his book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0143120174/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0143120174&linkCode=as2&tag=diplateevo-20&linkId=HR5CUPMGSMQQ6H2W" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">What Technology Wants</a>. This blog post is basically a compilation of my thoughts and lessons gleaned from reading the book, I am not taking credit for any of the thinking.</p><p>Essentially, the technium describes a kingdom of species, much like the other six kingdoms of living things. It is the entire network and collection of all the tools that have ever been created and utilized, including culture, art, social institutions, and intellectual creation of all types.</p><p>At first glance, it might seem a little strange to consider technology as a kingdom of life, but when considered as such, it becomes easier to recognize different trends and understand where technology came from and where it is going.</p><h2 id="the-power-of-a-meme">The Power of a Meme</h2><p>The most significant transitions in human history have all centered around a revolution in the ways that we communicate. Communication, the fundamental method in which people share thoughts, is the building block on top of which humans have been able to build and accomplish the things that we have. In the same way that a gene is the building block for biological life, memes are the building blocks for technology.</p><p>The first revolution in communication happened when humans began vocally transmitting ideas to each other. By creating language, people are able to quickly and easy share thoughts from one person to another. Having a common language changed everything, and can be considered the first singularity for humans.</p><blockquote><p>“Language is a trick that allows the mind to question itself; a magic mirror that reveals to the mind what the mind thinks; a handle that turns a mind into a tool.” – Kevin Kelly</p></blockquote><p>The next revolution in communication happened when spoken language became written language. All of a sudden, humans developed a way not only to physically transmit thoughts to someone who was in the range of your vocal chords, we developed a way to share thoughts at a distance of both time and space.</p><p>Having a written language was powerful, but still limited by how much a single person could write. With the invention of the printing press, books could now be made for a fraction of the cost, and suddenly one person could speak to a massive number of people.</p><p>Not too long after came the radio, broadcast television, and other media, causing yet another shift in the way that technology enable humans to communicate with each other.</p><p>And finally, the most recent innovation that is completely changing the way that people communicate has been the digitization of content and the network of computers that have permeated the 21st century.</p><p>The implications of going from a non linguistic culture to a linguistic culture to a digital culture are huge. It’s not just that the technological landscape is different, it’s that humans operate in a fundamentally different way. Language is an inseparable aspect of the human experience.</p><h2 id="exponential-growth">Exponential Growth</h2><p>However, there are many attributes of the technium that make it drastically different than any biological kingdom. While biology undergoes a natural linear process of evolution, technology evolves at an exponential rate, causing a vastly different trajectory.</p><p><a href="http://www.wikiwand.com/en/Moore%27s_law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Moore’s law</a> explains that every 18 months, for the same price point, the power of the technology that you can buy doubles. We see this trend in processing power, disk space, etc. It wasn’t that long ago that 128MB microSD cards were considered large.</p><p>Because technology advances at an exponential rate, the evolution and development increases at a rate that most people have an extremely difficult time wrapping their minds around. Humans are naturally local and linear thinkers, because humans evolved in a world in which the things that mattered to an individual happened right next to them. Additionally, there was minimal change from generation to generation, establishing cultures that by nature, do not adapt well to change.</p><p>I recommend reading <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/145161683X/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=145161683X&linkCode=as2&tag=diplateevo-20&linkId=SNIK24X4THLPH7DT" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Abundance by Peter Diamandis and Steven Kotler</a> for more on this.</p><h2 id="exotropy">Exotropy</h2><p>Kelly describes exotropy as negative entropy. In other words, the reversal of disorder. Everything, including technology, follows an exotropic progression, bringing more diversity into the world with each step of evolution. From the first few moments of the existence of the universe where there existed only particles of very basic elements, the universe has self organized into galaxies, planets, and different forms of life.</p><blockquote><p>“Exotropy is neither wave nor particle, nor pure energy, nor supernatural miracle. It is an immaterial flow that is very much like information. Since exotropy is defined as negative entropy – the reversal of disorder – it is, by definition, an increase in order.” – Kevin Kelly</p></blockquote><p>As a result of Moore’s law and the nature of technological progress, technology increases the rate of exotropy in the universe. While biological systems can only evolve incrementally with a couple genetic changes every generation, technology is only restricted by mankind’s ability to innovate.</p><p>Technological exotropy can be seen in the enormous diversity of different technological species that exist in the world today. Technology allowed us to accomplish a more diverse set of tasks that nature has not been able to achieve, such as space travel, supersonic flight, seamless ubiquitous communication, etc.</p><p>The phenomena produces a powerful cycle of scaffolding, in which the tools that we build help us build better tools in an endless cycle of exponential improvement. Where as biological systems can only make improvements at a marginal rate, technology enables at a much more exponential pace.</p><h2 id="coevolution">Coevolution</h2><p>On one side of global progress is the development of technology, but there is a whole other side, the development of humans, that is not as frequently talked about nor thought about. The very tools that humans spend their lives developing and building, the tools also deeply change the way that we do life. It’s impossible to imagine life without language, because language is a technology that has reached ubiquity in the human race, being integrated deep into everything that we do.</p><p>As humans simultaneously develop with technology, there is a whole body of literature that argues the convergence of humanity and technology known as <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0143037889/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0143037889&linkCode=as2&tag=diplateevo-20&linkId=M5IJ6Q7AQRONPI2D" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the singularity</a>. Popularized by inventor Ray Kurzweil, the singularity refers to a point in time in which man and machine are indistinguishable from each other. According to Kurzweil, the singularity will take place by 2045.</p><p>Regardless of whether you believe the singularity will happen in the next 30 years, getting to the singularity implies a great deal of change that depends on how quickly humans are able to adapt. The problem isn’t that technologies aren’t being invented fast enough, the problem is that humans aren’t learning how to use technologies fast enough.</p><p>One of the clearest examples of coevolution is the development of cities, Kelly calls cities “technological artifacts, the largest technology we make”. With cities, humans literally build and evolve the world around them. We create modes of transportation, urban environments, and all sorts of experiences ranging from museums to academic institutions to restaurants and more. As our space around us changes, so does the way that we live our lives. In fact, most city dwellers would not survive a couple days in the wilderness.</p><h2 id="multiple-evolution">Multiple Evolution</h2><p>Multiple evolution is a concept that is rarely articulated, but a phenomena that deeply affects the progress and discoveries of life. Multiple evolution is the idea that multiple innovations evolve in a simultaneously independent manner. This happens in every field from art, literature, research, technology, biology and more.</p><p>For example, the infamous story of Harry Potter was not the only book written about boy wizards in magical schools with pet owls who enter other worlds through railway station platforms. In fact, there are arguably a few authors who have written books of the same nature at the same time without any knowledge of each other’s existence.</p><p>It becomes interesting when you realize that not only works of literature, but many scientific and technological discoveries and innovations, although not implemented in an identical manner, were developed simultaneously. Calculus was developed by Newton and Liebniz, Darwin was not the sole fabricator of evolution, etc etc.</p><p>This supports the idea that technological evolution inevitably progresses in a certain direction, because if one innovator didn’t invent a particular technology, chances are someone else would have. This also supports the concept that technology has it’s own evolutionary tendencies independent of the input of any single human being.</p><p>One explanation for this phenomenon is that the development of technologies follow a sequence in which all innovation depends on a previous innovation, and it comes down to nothing but a matter of time. You can’t do calculus unless you know how to count. In the same way, television and radio would never have been developed without the printing press, and the development of computers means that a network of computers would inevitably happen.</p><h2 id="social-and-political-implications">Social and Political Implications</h2><p>Of course, it would be irresponsible to talk about the evolution of technology without talking about the social and political implications that technology creates. The elephant in the room is that the affluent individuals with access to technology create an extremely large opportunity gap between them and people who may not have enough resources to be on the cutting edge.</p><p>As a result of technology, the disparity between modern societies and traditional societies are enormous. The disparity caused by such an inequality between people with access to technology and people without has implications in economics, health, and the overall standard of living.</p><p>However, because of the exponential nature of technology, individuals who are behind on the technological curve do not remain in the dark forever. Like the inevitability of developments, it is only a matter of time before a technology reaches ubiquity among the entire human population.</p><p>In the case of the internet, conservative estimates are that the majority of the world will be on the internet in the next few years. This is significant, because the internet will soon become flooded with billions of people coming online in the next few years.</p><p>Thus, the question when it comes to social and political implications is not what to do with the disparity, but how to increase the speed that a technology reaches ubiquity.</p><h2 id="new-platforms-for-art-and-expression">New Platforms for Art and Expression</h2><p>One observation that I’ve made is that as technology advances, it creates more mediums for human expression, which can also be considered a form of technology. In many ways, function and form, especially when it comes to our technology, are becoming increasingly inseparable.</p><p>New technologies are constantly disrupting old ones and changing the way that we express ourselves. By lowering the barrier of entry to traditionally hard to enter industries, technology allows anyone to share thoughts, connect with people, create media, etc etc.</p><p><a href="http://www.sethgodin.com/sg/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Seth Godin</a> famously calls this the era of the “connection economy”, in which value no longer resides in having knowledge, but in being able to synthesize and connect different things in order to creatively innovate new products, services, and ideas.</p><h2 id="applying-new-technologies">Applying New Technologies</h2><p>As new technology is applied, a couple things happen. Firstly, most technology is never applied exactly how the inventor imagined it, oftentimes being applied in completely different ways to achieve completely different results. Thus, it is impossible for an inventor of a technology to fully understand the implications of his creation let alone what it will be used for.</p><p>For instance, when television first came out, television programs were nothing more than recorded broadway shows being aired, leaving the full potential of television completely untapped. The inventor of the television did not foresee the application of such a technology to all the different uses that it is being used for today.</p><p>Secondly, the implications of any piece of technology upon culture is extremely hard to foresee. For example, the inventor of the car probably would not have imagined the whole infrastructure of roads, streetlights, gas stations, car dealers, traffic jams, insurance, etc that exist today.</p><p>This leads to a very interesting situation, in which it is difficult to predict exactly how revolutionary a certain new technology will be until we are literally on the verge of implementing the technology in a way that changes everything. And any technology that can be used to completely revolutionize the world can also be abused, meaning that it is inherently impossible to have full control over the technium.</p><h2 id="a-value-system-applied-to-technology">A Value System Applied to Technology</h2><p>Even though technology has an inevitable progression, it is very possible to apply a value system to steer technology in a way that is favorable to improving the human condition. The amish, a group of people who live with very little technology, exemplify how it is possible to live in a modern day world while having a very specific value system guiding their technology use.</p><p>With the understanding that any technology that is revolutionary can also have immense consequences, the amish are very cautious to introduce a new technology that might detract from their emphasis on community. However, despite the fact that they do not adapt most technologies, the amish are quite knowledgable about the technology that is going on in the world.</p><p>There’s a whole system in place in order to maintain the integrity of their social and religious values, in which community members are allowed to petition to test new technologies in their personal lives while being observed by the rest of the community to see how the particular technology impacts the community as a whole.</p><p>The amish do not live outside of technology, the live inside the technium in such a way where they slow it down, not stopping it entirely. Through this experience of elective poverty and minimalism, they are able to maximize their ultimate goals of valuing community.</p><blockquote><p>“To maximize our own contentment, we seek the minimum amount of technology in our lives. Yet to maximize the contentment of others, we must maximize the amount of technology in the world.” – Kevin Kelly</p></blockquote><p>Thus, just because a technology has the potential to be harmful, that doesn’t mean that we should avoid it altogether. Every technology has benefits as well as drawbacks, but as long there is slightly more upside than downside, we shouldn’t completely ignore new innovations.</p><h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2><p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0143120174/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0143120174&linkCode=as2&tag=diplateevo-20&linkId=HR5CUPMGSMQQ6H2W" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">What Technology Wants</a> has been one of the books that have introduced many new concepts in a way that got me thinking a lot about the world that we live in. It is truly a book with very convincing insights about technology and more importantly the human experience and human condition.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <enclosure url="https://www.diplateevo.com/images/2021/01/battery-camera-canon-261.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>